Guide to the Alexander Mordecai Bickel Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- COMMITTEES, 1966-1974; Series VIII; 2 linear feet (5 boxes)
  - Caseload Study Group
    - John P. Frank, member, Advisory Council on Appellate Justice: 'Freund Committee Report", 1973 January 9 (Box 36, Folder 12)
    - Members: letters, 1972 December 20-1973 February 5 (Box 36, Folder 12)
    - Warren E. Burger: correspondence, 1973 February 10-16, June 6 (Box 36, Folder 13)
    - Advisory Council for Appellate Justice:
      - "Expediting Review of Felony Convictions after Trial: Report No. 1 of the Committee on Criminal Appeals", 1973 February (Box 36, Folder 13)
      - "Unification of the National Appellate Courts: A Statement to the Congressional Commission on the Organization of the Federal Courts", 1973 March 6 (Box 36, Folder 13)
    - Members: correspondence, 1973 March 13-December 6 (Box 36, Folder 13)
    - A. Bickel: notes, 1972-1973, undated (Box 36, Folder 13)
    - William O. Douglas: "Remarks" before the New York City Bar Association, 1970 March 19 (Box 36, Folder 14)
    - Charles A. Wright: statement to the Senate Judiciary Subcommittee on Improvements in Judicial machinery, 1972 May 16 (Box 36, Folder 14)
    - Warren E. Burger: "Has the Time Come?", 1972 May 16 (Box 36, Folder 14)
    - Lewis F. Powell, Jr.: "An Overburdened Supreme Court", 1972 June 30 (Box 36, Folder 14)
    - Warren E. Burger: "Report on the Problems of the Judiciary", 1972 August 14 (Box 36, Folder 14)
    - Lewis F. Powell, Jr.: excerpts from informal talk, Fifth Circuit Judicial Conference, 1973 April 11 (Box 36, Folder 15)
    - Carl McGowan: remarks before the New York City Bar Association, 1973 April 23 (Box 36, Folder 15)
    - Earl Warren: address to the New York City Bar Association, 1973 May 1 (Box 36, Folder 15)
    - Warren E. Burger: "Observations on the Report of the Study Group on the Caseload of the Supreme Court", 1973 May 15 (Box 36, Folder 15)
    - William J. Brennan, Jr.: "The National Court of Appeals: Another Dissent", 1973 May 23 (Box 36, Folder 16)
    - Chicago Council of Lawyers: "Report on the Proposals of the Study Group …" and related letters, 1973 pre-July 31 (Box 36, Folder 16)
    - Warren E. Burger: "Report on the Federal Judicial Branch", 1973 August 6 (Box 36, Folder 16)
    - Paul A. Freund; "A National Court of Appeals", 1973 August 7 (Box 36, Folder 16)
    - Erwin N. Griswold: "The Supreme Court's Case Load: Civil Rights and Other Problems", 1973 November 8 (Box 36, Folder 16)
    - American Bar Association, Special Committee on Coordination of Judicial Improvements: reports, undated (Box 37, Folder 17)
    - Clippings, 1972 August-1973 November (Box 37, Folder 18)
    - U. S. Supreme Court: caseload statistics, 1971-1973, undated (Box 37, Folder 19)
  - Civil Litigation Advisory Group
    - Warren E. Burger: correspondence and speeches, 1968 September 4, 1970 July 20-1971 January 12 (Box 37, Folder 20)
    - Warren E. Burger: letters and speeches, 1971 Apr, September (Box 37, Folder 21)
    - Members and staff: letters and memoranda, 1971 January-February (Box 37, Folder 22)
    - Members: memoranda, 1971 February 18-March 8 (Box 37, Folder 23)
    - "Exchange of correspondence between Professor Charles Alan Wright and William Eldridge re the Time Burden of Jury and Non-Jury Cases", 1971 February 1-March 5 (Box 37, Folder 23)
    - Jack B. Weinstein: letters, 1971 March 1-18 (Box 37, Folder 24)
    - Federal Judicial Center: "Third Midyear Report", 1971 March 1 (Box 37, Folder 25)
    - Shirley M. Hufstedler: "New Blocks for Old Pyramids: Reshaping the Judicial System", 1971 March 18 (Box 37, Folder 25)
    - Members and staff: letters and working outlines, 1971 March 22-May 10 (Box 37, Folder 26)
    - "'Free Bird's' Report on Civil Litigation: Initial Draft", 1971 May 28 (Box 37, Folder 27)
    - Members: letters, 1971 June 2, 9 (Box 37, Folder 27)
    - "Suggestions for Improving the Processes of Civil Litigation in the Federal Courts: Third Draft", 1971 June 15 (Box 37, Folder 28)
    - Jack B. Weinstein: letter, 1971 June 22 (Box 37, Folder 28)
    - "Suggestions for Improving the Processes of Civil Litigation in the Federal Courts …: A Tentative Report by the Chief Justice's Special Advisory Group on Federal Civil Litigation", 1971 June 30 (Box 37, Folder 29)
  - Committee for the Formation of the New Party
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 1968 July 28-September 26, undated (Box 37, Folder 30)
    - A. Bickel: "Fourth Party Legal Problems", 1968 July 31 (Box 37, Folder 31)
    - A. Bickel: notes, undated (Box 37, Folder 31)
    - Charles Fishman, research assistant, Institute for Policy Studies: "The Election Laws of the Fifty States", undated (Box 38, Folder 32)
    - Judicial opinions related to state election laws, 1966-1968 (Box 38, Folder 33)
  - Hughes Commission
    - Organizational papers and research material, 1968 August 2-September 6, undated (Box 38, Folder 34)
    - A. Bickel: three drafts of testimony before the Credentials Committee of the Democratic National Convention, 1968 August 19 (Box 38, Folder 35)
    - A. Bickel: memorandum, "Reforming the National Convention", undated (Box 38, Folder 35)
    - "Commission Report: Working Draft", 1968 (Box 38, Folder 36)
    - "Summary of Findings and Advisory Report", 1968 (Box 38, Folder 37)
    - The Democratic Choice: A Report of the Commission …, 1968 (Box 38, Folder 37)
    - John R. Schmidt and Wayne W. Whalen: correspondence, 1968 October (Box 38, Folder 38)
    - Joseph L. Rauh, Jr.: correspondence, 1969 January-February (Box 38, Folder 38)
    - Harold E. Hughes; correspondence, 1969 January-March (Box 38, Folder 38)
    - James Loeb, Jr.: correspondence, 1969 February (Box 38, Folder 38)
    - Geoffrey Cowan: correspondence, 1969 August-October (Box 38, Folder 38)
  - McGovern Commission
    - Thomas P. Alder: letter, [1969 February 26?] (Box 38, Folder 39)
    - George S. McGovern: correspondence, 1969 March 6-12 (Box 38, Folder 39)
    - Frederick G. Dutton: correspondence, 1969 March 7-28 (Box 38, Folder 39)
    - Organizational papers, 1969 Feb, undated (Box 38, Folder 40)
    - Summaries and transcripts of first meeting, 1969 March 1 (Box 38, Folder 40)
    - Press releases, 1969 March 2l-April 25 (Box 38, Folder 40)
    - G. McGovern: correspondence, 1969 June (Box 38, Folder 41)
    - Staff: correspondence, 1969 June-October (Box 38, Folder 41)
    - Donald M. Fraser: draft finding on "Proportionality", [1969 Oct?] (Box 38, Folder 41)
    - A. Bickel: notes, [1969 Jul?, Oct?] (Box 38, Folder 41)
    - A. Bickel: "Fair Representation of Minority Political Views", 1969 October 13 (Box 38, Folder 42)
    - Richard C. Wade: "Apportionment", [1969 Oct?] (Box 38, Folder 42)
    - Draft findings, [1969?] (Box 38, Folder 43)
    - G. McGovern: letters, 1970 June 29, July 9 (Box 38, Folder 44)
    - A. Bickel: memorandum for file, 1971 post-February 19 (Box 38, Folder 44)
    - Chicago Challengers: request for ruling, 1972 May 10 (Box 38, Folder 44)
    - A. Bickel to Theodore H. White:
      - letter, 1972 October 3 (Box 38, Folder 45)
      - testimony before the Credentials Committee of the Democratic National Convention, 1968 August 19 (Box 38, Folder 45)
      - memorandum of conversation with G. McGovern, 1969 March 5 (Box 38, Folder 45)
      - staff memorandum, "Task Force Hearing Themes", 1969 May 27 (Box 38, Folder 45)
      - "First Report Outline", 1969 July 31 (Box 38, Folder 45)
      - notes on meeting, 1969 September 23 (Box 38, Folder 45)
      - letter to G. McGovern, 1969 October 24 (Box 38, Folder 45)
      - circular letter by G. McGovern, 1969 October 3 (Box 38, Folder 45)
      - letter to G. McGovern, 1969 August 19 (Box 38, Folder 45)
      - correspondence with R. Wade, 1969 October 22-November 5 (Box 38, Folder 45)
      - staff memorandum, "Clarifying language and suggested substantive changes", 1969 November 13 (Box 38, Folder 45)
      - chairman's memorandum, "Representation of Women, Young People and Minorities", 1971 December 9 (Box 38, Folder 45)
    - Staff: memoranda, 1969 June-Nov, [1969?], 1969 December-1970 Jan, 1970 July-1972 June (Box 38, Folder 46-48)
    - Memorandum for state organizations, "Model of Party Rules", 1971 post-February 19 (Box 38, Folder 49)
    - "The Party Reformed: Final Report", 1972 July 7 (Box 39, Folder 50)
    - Reports on delegate selection procedures, Connecticut to Massachusetts, 1969 (Box 39, Folder 51)
    - Reports on delegate selection procedures, Michigan to Missouri, 1969 (Box 39, Folder 52)
    - Reports on delegate selection procedures, New York to Rhode Island, 1969 (Box 39, Folder 53)
    - Reports on delegate selection procedures, South Dakota and Wisconsin, 1969 (Box 39, Folder 54)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Brandeis Papers Commission:
      - correspondence, 1967 August 4-1971 February 3 (Box 39, Folder 55)
      - note by A Bickel, undated (Box 39, Folder 55)
      - memoranda by William M. Goldsmith, acting director of the editorial project, pre-1968 February 29 (Box 39, Folder 56)
    - Connecticut Bar Association, Judiciary Committee, Judicial Selection Subcommittee: letters and minutes, 1966 November 15-1967 May 15 (Box 39, Folder 57)
    - Frankfurter Papers:
      - correspondence, 1954, 1959, 1965-1970 May (Box 39, Folder 58-60)
      - correspondence, 1970 June-1972 October (Box 39, Folder 61)
    - Harvard Law School, Visiting Committee:
      - correspondence and memoranda, 1968 January 31-June 21 (Box 39, Folder 62)
      - correspondence, leaflets, and memoranda, 1968 December 9-1969 June 24 (Box 39, Folder 63)
      - correspondence, leaflets, and reports, 1970 February 17-1974 June 14 (Box 39, Folder 64)
    - Harvard University Press, Faculty Prize Committee: correspondence and notes, 1969 February 20-May 23 (Box 40, Folder 65)
    - Lehrman Institute, Board of Trustees: correspondence and memoranda, 1972 October 6-1974 December 9 (Box 40, Folder 66)
  - O'Hara Commission
    - James G. O'Hara: correspondence, 1969 April 24-May 13 (Box 40, Folder 67)
    - Leaflets, 1969 May 17 (Box 40, Folder 67)
    - Paul T. David: prepared statement, 1969 May 17 (Box 40, Folder 67)
    - A. Bickel: prepared statement, 1969 May 17 (Box 40, Folder 67)
    - Robert G. Dixon, Jr.; prepared statement, 1969 May 17 (Box 40, Folder 67)
    - List of procedures, 1969 May 17 (Box 40, Folder 67)
    - J. O'Hara: letter, 1969 May 22 (Box 40, Folder 67)
    - Joseph F. Crangle, chairman, Erie County [New York] Democratic Committee: correspondence, 1969 May 29-June 6 (Box 40, Folder 67)
    - J. O'Hara: correspondence, 1969 October 22-1970 April 28 (Box 40, Folder 67)
    - Issues and Alternatives: A Study Guide of Democratic National Convention Procedure and Practice, 1969 October (Box 40, Folder 68)
    - Memoranda, testimony, press releases, and clippings, 1969 December 7-1972 Mar, undated (Box 40, Folder 69)
- CONFERENCES, 1967-1972; Series IX; 1 linear feet (2 boxes)
  Series IX, CONFERENCES, relates to meetings sponsored by foundations and study centers for discussion of legal, political, and social problems: planning for the year 2000, medical experimentation on humans, government reogranization, civil disorder, the electoral process, and regulation of the press. The papers consist of correspondence with conference organizers, working papers prepared by participants, and transcripts of proceedings. The transcripts of the Conference on the Ethical Aspects of Experimentation with Human Subjects and the two meetings of the Working Party on Rights and Values of the Commission on the Year 2000 show Bickel as a major contributor to the discussion.
  The conference sponsors are in alphabetical order. The papers related to any particular conference are in chronological order except that items not connected with any particular phase of the activity are at the end.
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, Commission on the year 2000, Working Party on Rights and Values:
    - transcript of meeting, 1967 May 12-13, November 10-11 (Box 41, Folder 1-2)
  - Aspen Workshop on Communications and Society, Seminar on Government and Media Relations: correspondence and memoranda, 1972 June 13-September 6, undated (Box 41, Folder 3)
  - Brookings Institution, Conference on the Report of the President's Advisory Commission on Executive Organization:
    - correspondence, memoranda, and summary of discussion, 1971 March 9-April 23 (Box 41, Folder 4)
    - Roger G. Noll, Summary of the report, 1971 April (Box 41, Folder 5)
  - Daedalus and the National Institutes of Health, Conference on the Ethical Aspects of Experimentation on Human Subjects: correspondence and transcript of proceedings, 1967 November 3-4 (Box 41, Folder 6)
  - Ford Foundation and Carnegie Foundation, Electoral Process Conference:
    - correspondence and minutes of meeting, 1969 January 7-February 4 (Box 41, Folder 7)
    - Institute of Public Affairs, "Interim Report: Electoral Process Study", 1969 January 20 (Box 41, Folder 8)
  - Kenyon College, Public Affairs Conference Center, Conference on Civil Disobedience:
    - readings, 1968 (Box 42, Folder 8a)
  - Kenyon College, Public Affairs Conference Center, Conference on Censorship and Freedom of Expression:
    - correspondence and readings, 1969 August 22-1970 June 18 (Box 42, Folder 9)
    - readings, 1970 pre-April 20 (Box 42, Folder 10)
  - Kenyon College, Public Affairs Conference Center, Conference on Civil Disorder and Violence in the United States:
    - correspondence, notes, and readings, 1970 October 9-1971 May 3 (Box 42, Folder 11)
- LEGAL PRACTICE, 1950, 1954, 1967-1974; Series X; 7 linear feet (16 boxes)
  Series X, LEGAL PRACTICE, consists of correspondence among lawyers, drafts of briefs and other legal writings, notes for oral argument, and legal papers and research material forwarded to Bickel by the attorneys with whom he collaborated and by others concerned in the cases. The correspondence is mainly routine, and neither the letters nor the enclosures add much to the formal statements of the facts. The special value of these papers lies rather in their resources for the study of Bickel's legal work. His service as law clerk is represented by his memorandum, "The Search and Seizure Issue," for Judge Magruder in Best v. United States. (His better-known memorandum for Justice Frankfurter in Brown v. Board of Education is in Series IV with other papers related to his law review article, "The Original Understanding and the Segregation Decision" [1955].) The rest of the papers relate to his own formal and informal practice.
  The cases that most concerned Bickel as journalist and adviser to government officials were suits brought on behalf of black children to achieve desegregation of public schools. He was reluctant, however, to take part in such litigation because he did not want to risk compromising his reputation as a disinterested observer ( United States v. Indianapolis School Board, 1972 Mar 16). When he did participate, he did so as a consultant, not appearing as a witness or being named as attorney of record. This series has sections related to three cases involving school desegregation; Swann v. Charlotte-Mecklenburg, United States v. Indianapolis School Board, and Spangler v. Pasadena City Board of Education.
  Bickel participated in Swann v. Charlotte:-Mecklenburg by providing the Congress of Racial Equality (CORE) with an "Outline and Prospectus" of a brief amicus curiae to be filed with the United States Supreme Court. He argued that the constitutional obligation of "disestablishment of legally enforced segregation" did not require "enforcement by law of racial dispersal in the schools." The papers in this section include the "Outline and prospectus," CORE's brief amicus curiae, the Supreme Court's slip opinion annotated by Bickel, and his correspondence with Roy Innis, national director of CORE. Bickel elaborated the distinction in the prospectus and interpreted the Supreme Court's decision for the Senate Select Committee on Equal Educational Opportunity (Series VI, School Desegregation, 1970 Sep 24, 1971 Jun 15).
  In January 1970, the United States District Court closed the first phase of Spangler v. Pasadena City Board of Education by requiring the board to arrange that no minority constitute a majority in any Pasadena public school. The documentation of Bickel's interest begins a year later, with his first exchange of letters with Henry Marcheschi, a Pasadena businessman then conducting a successful campaign for a seat on the board as an opponent of forced busing away from neighborhood schools. His correspondence with Bickel between 1971 and 1974 deals with developments in Pasadena and with Bickel's collaboration with Congressman Richardson Preyer in drafting legislation to foster alternatives to the sort of plan the District Court had prescribed for Pasadena. Marcheschi also transmitted legal papers connected with the case and his own exposition of a plan to achieve "Voluntary Integration and Equal Educational Opportunity" while respecting the principle of neighborhood schools.
  When the Pasadena School Board decided in October 1973 to petition for modification of the District Court order, its attorneys began consulting with Bickel. From then until his death, Bickel was kept informed about the progress of the case, and he advised intermittently on its management. The papers belonging to this period of collaboration consist almost exclusively of letters addressed to Bickel and documents connected with the litigation. With the exception of an analysis (1974 May 18) of the court's opinion and order in response to the board's petition (May 3), Bickel's advice must be reconstructed from references in the letters he received.
  Bickel agreed to participate in United States v. Indianapolis School Board following an interim order (1973 Jul 20) of the United States District Court that certain suburban school districts assist in desegregating the Indianapolis public schools by accepting black children transferred from the city. The attorneys for the affected school districts had immediately begun an appeal, but at his suggestion they applied for a stay of proceedings pending the entry of a final order by the District Court. To this application he contributed a critique of a motion for stay and supporting brief drafted by the Office of the Attorney General of Indiana. His other contributions, made in person or by telephone, can only be inferred from incoming letters. It was also at his suggestion that the Indiana attorneys decided to contribute a brief amicus curiae to the Detroit school desegregation case Bradley v. Milliken, but his final illness prevented his own participation. Nowhere in the papers does he discuss the District Court's desegregation plan.
  Closely related to the school desegregation cases was De Funis v. Odegaard, in which a white citizen of Washington State sued for admission to the state university law school, claiming that in denying his application it had unconstitutionally discriminated against him because of his race. Bickel first took part in the summer of 1973, when De Funis's attorneys were preparing to appeal the decision of the Washington State Supreme Court to the Supreme Court of the United States. He was retained by the Anti-Defamation League of B'nai B'rith, on whose behalf he drafted two briefs amicus curiae. The first supported the appeal and the alternative petition for certiorari; the second, finished by a colleague, argued the case on the merits. Among the papers are attorneys' correspondence, briefs filed with the Supreme Court by the Anti-Defamation League and several other amici, and some of the documents filed with the state courts at various stages in the litigation. The United States Supreme Court remanded the matter to the Supreme Court of Washington for further proceedings, but Bickel did not take part in this later stage of the case.
  Two other matters raised Fourteenth-Amendment questions in contexts having nothing to do with race. The more substantial of these was the New Jersey Contingent Fees case, a pair of suits brought by trial lawyers to oppose the State Supreme Court's recently established schedule for determining the amount due the attorney when the fee was contingent on the size of the settlement. Bickel participated virtually from the beginning and played a large role in the day-to-day management of the case. The litigation followed a complicated course, moving repeatedly between the state and federal courts and up and down within each system, and procedural and jurisdictional problems were correspondingly prominent. Bickel was equally concerned with these matters and with the constitutional questions the new regulation raised, particularly with regard to the equal protection and due process clauses of the Fourteenth Amendment and the clause in the New Jersey Constitution regarding judicial rule-making. The principal items documenting his contribution are letters, drafts, and notes for oral argument. Much of the consultation with fellow attorneys took place in meetings or over the telephone, but the letters are more informative than most of his legal correspondence. The papers also include briefs, motions, and opinions pertaining to every stage in the litigation.
  Some of the same constitutional questions were considered in the Connecticut Credit Rate Research Project, in which Bickel was retained with another lawyer to study the prospects for successful litigation against a state statute allowing retailers to charge no more than one per cent monthly interest in open-credit plans. They concluded that the statute might be held to violate the equal protection clause of the Fourteenth Amendment by not imposing the same requirement on other lenders, but advised that the courts would probably reject this interpretation. The papers in this section consist of research material, correspondence, and draft and final versions of the commissioned memorandum.
  The free-speech and free-press guarantees of the First Amendment were a second focus of Bickel's legal career. In New York Times Co. v. United States (the Pentagon Papers case) and in several other matters commanding national attention, he argued for the protection of the First Amendment. In Buckley v. AFTRA and Lewis v. AFTRA, he defended the position of the American Federation of Television and Radio Artists that it could require commentators on public affairs to pay membership costs without abridging their First Amendment rights.